[Music]
hey hey welcome back
it is day four uh of our week two coding
camp
uh today's activity is going to be
called slide puzzle
i'm here with my campers as per usual
i'll let them go ahead and introduce
themselves
hello my name is keegan fisher hi
i'm mckenley you seem asleep today
mckenna are you ready to code today
is it too early for you today all right
we're uh we're ready to go today uh so
today
uh is called slide puzzle uh and it's
gonna start just a little bit different
in that i normally show you the solution
uh but today what i want you to do is i
want you to open the solution and play
with it
and so the the link is uh is clickable
there but i think it's probably easiest
if you just kind of look at the real
link so i'm going to make this link
available below the
the video in the email also on the
website but worst case scenario you can
look at my screen and type it here so
it's scratch.mit.edu
projects and then this number is
537-036-624
and this is called a slide puzzle with
check solve
all right so let's go ahead and uh play
this game uh to learn more about it
so go ahead and uh hit the green flag
um and so what this puzzle is it's
called a slide puzzle
you click on a piece and you make it go
into the gap
and your goal is you want to try to get
the puzzle to be rearranged properly
again
so take a minute and play with it and
see if you can make progress
uh towards getting it rearranged my
strategy is i always do the opening row
first you'll notice that each of these
tiles has kind of
got a number on it so you'll know when
it's right
and then mine's going to actually be
pretty easy to solve here just a couple
more
uh so one more click and i'm gonna solve
this thing i can tell so you'll notice
that there's a three by three grid
uh but there's only eight image tiles
present
because one has to be gone for the blank
but when you solve it
it should cheer for you loudly as per
usual
and then fill in uh that missing blank
so take a minute
uh and play around with it you'll notice
that whenever you hit the green flag
it'll kind of shuffle around what we
actually want to do first today
is we want to show you the game that
we're making which is which is this game
here
but we want to teach you an algorithm
for solving it
also just kind of like spoiler the goal
for today is for you to make your own
picture in here so be thinking about
what picture
you might want to put in here it could
be a picture like that you took like
with a camera picture
or it could be just like some image that
you enjoy doing
so let's learn um an algorithm for
trying to solve this thing
so i'm going to go over to the slides
here so the algorithm
um that we're trying to figure out is
how to solve this one row at a time
and so i'm just going to tell you the
big picture so the the first few steps
are designed to help you get
tiles one two and three correct so
that's that's the focus
whenever you're working on tiles one two
and three you also need the row below it
to get ready
this algorithm will work no matter how
big the puzzle is right so you've got
one row you're trying to solve for
and then the row you're kind of working
with below it and ultimately you're
trying to get them
one two and three together but we're
going to kind of stage them starting in
location six which is kind of the
opposite corner so here's the solving
strategy we're going to do
get tile number one so this is tile
number one the one that's got it one on
it
into location six and so you can see
we've numbered the locations one two
three four five six seven eight nine
so we want to get tile one into location
six making sure that tiles
two isn't like stuck in positions three
or six
so uh go ahead and do that i'll go ahead
and do mine as well
so i can see that that tile two is
somewhere way over here so he's way out
of the way so i'm not even worried about
him
and then i'm just going to get tile one
so this is tile one right here into
location six
making sure that tile two isn't trapped
so tile two is is not trapped
um trapped would be like so see how tile
five here is kind of like trapped up
there
and tile six it's kind of like trapped
down here so long as tile two
isn't like that you should be in good
shape
the next step after this this is the
algorithm
by the way has anybody ever solved a
rubik's cube i know that my kids have
rubik's cubes are really tricky and so
like you can just play with rubik's
cubes to your heart's content but you
may not ever make progress
but if you have one of these algorithms
for solving a rubik's cube
you'll probably be successful and since
this is a coding camp
being able to implement algorithms is is
good for us to learn anyway
so the first step in the algorithm is to
get tile 1 to location 6.
the next step in the algorithm is pretty
easy move
tile 2 into location 5. so i just want
to get tile 2 to be right next to it
and this may seem kind of weird at first
but you'll hopefully understand the
the reasons behind this but we're trying
to stage these tile
1 2 because we're trying to like get
this top row together all right so i've
got tile 2 in the middle looks like my
campers are caught up so that's good
uh the next step is we want to kind of
slide one and two around a little bit
so tile one you can see had to go up one
spot
tile two had to like follow it around
and do that and make sure that tile
three is not like stuck in the bottom
uh when you do this maneuver so first
i'm gonna find tile three
uh so it looks like he's way over here
so he's actually in good shape for me
if he was stuck like down here in
location six i would kind of have to
move him out first
but i want to move tile one up and tile
two over
making sure that tile three isn't stuck
so you can kind of see how
um six would be stuck in position nine
here like you couldn't get it out of
there
alright so now i'm ready for the next
step so i want to move tile three
into the middle uh so tile three needs
to go to that position five
this step should hopefully be a pretty
easy step presuming it was not stuck
so now i've kind of got one two three
they're kind of like a train
right so this train is ready to to move
around
the station by the way if i ever go too
fast just pause the video that's the
advantage of videos
so now with the train ready to move
around the bin
you just need to one by one march the
tiles one two and three around
such that tiles one two and three are in
locations one two and three
so i'm gonna go ahead and do that so i'm
just going to kind of merge them around
march march march march march uh now
one two and three are all correct the
way this algorithm works is it's very
like procedural
and so now we just finished that row now
we're ready for the next row down
and again this this algorithm would work
no matter how big this was if it was a
four by four it would work just the same
right you just have these um
like two rows at a time so now we're
going to try to solve the next row four
five and six
and we're going to use the row below it
as kind of like a helper
and the first step is to get uh tile
four uh to the lower right corner this
is actually
the same kind of thing we did before so
like before tile one started in position
6. and so this kind of like starts in
the opposite corner right
make sure that tile 5 is not stuck in
location 6.
so i'm going to make sure tile 5 is way
over here which it is
and i'm going to put 4 in the corner
great so i've got four in the opposite
corner of where it's going
and i got five not stuck the next step
is to put
five next to four this is very similar
to what the the thing we did in the row
before
so i'm going to put five next to four
don't even care how it gets there
so now i've got four and five down here
on the bottom
campers you got that cut up
and then i'm gonna move four up
and five over so i've got to move
four up and five over so i've got four
and five like the train's ready to go
around
uh and then i've got got to get tile six
into location eight
so tile six into location eight that was
actually pretty easy
and my puzzle is almost done it looks
like gibberish but it is almost done
because the last thing i have to do is i
have to march tiles four five and six
around like a train
um and then the neat thing is is that
seven and eight are guaranteed to be
correct which is kind of just neat how
it works out right
so i'm going to march these around
and then you can see that i finished
so see if you can do the algorithm again
on your own i'm not going to walk
through it again
but i can hear my camper solving it over
there
but the the steps and you can pause them
as you need is to get
tile one to location six i'm making sure
that two is not stuck
get one and two together uh march one
and two up one making sure
three isn't stuck putting three on the
train wagon
and then marching around and then we do
the same thing
with the next row down we get four which
is gonna eventually be up here in the
corner
making sure five is not stuck get five
next to four
start marching around get six uh
in the train and then you'll solve the
puzzle
sound good all right so uh hopefully
you've practiced that algorithm and
you're able to uh to implement that
algorithm
and you're ready to actually get started
today so
what we're going to start with is a
choice and so this choice
is do you want to customize this puzzle
or do you want to just remix one that we
give you i would recommend that you try
to customize this puzzle just because
it's more fun
so at the end of the day you'll have
like your own image and your own slide
puzzle
and you won't just use mine by the way
these uh these two girls
these are bob's girls and so this is bob
schaefer's family that you're seeing
here
but i think it'd be fun if it was
actually like like your stuff
so what i would recommend you do is
option number one you find your own
image
so something that you want to uh to make
into a slide puzzle
eventually uh we're gonna need nine
tiles for this image and we're gonna
show you the steps for this
where each tile has to be um 120 pixels
by 120 pixels
it's okay if it's like 119 or 121 but it
should be
pretty close right and i'm going to show
you the steps for that that is what i
recommend you do
if you don't think that's going to be
fun you can always
click on this remix link and i'll make
this remix link available to you
and what you can do is when you click on
this link there'll be a big button up
here that says remix and you can remix
this
but it already has these steps done so
if you have trouble making your own
so that's option three try your best to
do option number one but then if it
fails do option number
number one right all right so let's
show you these steps so the first thing
you need to do is you need
some website tools so there's two steps
in this process
one step is to resize the image such
that when it's chopped up
each little tile is 120 by 120 so we
need to resize the image
and then the second step is to chop it
up so i've gone on the internet and i
found some tools that do these things
so the first tool is simple
image resizer so you can if you've got
the link you can just click on this link
but if you needed to you could just do a
google search for
simple image resizer
hopefully the top hit is
simpleimageresizer.com right
um and so on this website is where
you're going to select your image
so now you need uh to pick some image so
for me
um i've got a lot of different images
that i could use i
normally i would just go on to like
photos.google.com
and i would just like find some recent
photo that i've done here so here's a
cool one with uh keegan the dog
yesterday
um here's some from our recent birthday
party
um and so you should somehow for you
find one of these images
i'll tell you what i'll just go ahead
and click on one of these make sure my
wife looks good in it
and click download and so i'm going to
save this into
uh fisher birthday so now i've got
my image that i'm using you should do
your own thing to get your image
and then you're going to go into simple
image resizer and you're going to say
select image
and so mine was called fisher birthday
and you're going to upload it now i was
a little fast
because i should have known something
about this image before i got this far
i should know which dimension is smaller
so
in this picture this is a landscape
picture the smaller dimension is the
height
and so whichever dimension is smaller
you need to get that in your head so for
me
it's height so on this tool i'm going to
say
there's a radio for percentage or
dimension i want to mention
and then whichever of your dimensions is
smaller make that one three
six zero so if you've got a portrait
image make your width
three six zero if you've got a landscape
image like me
uh so again this is my landscape image
so the height is smaller
so i want the smaller dimension to be
360. and the reason for that is that way
the other dimension is guaranteed to be
something bigger right which is good
and then you click on resize
and then you said it's been resized and
then it says click here to download it
so you click on this download button
now strangely it doesn't actually
download it like wouldn't you think that
a download button
would download it raise your hand over
there campers if you think download
should download it
it doesn't it opens it in a new tab in
chrome
it does resize it which is good but now
you need to download it so i'm going to
right click on it
and i'm going to say save image as
um and so this uh got the same name
fisher birthday and then it added this
x360 so that looks good
so there are a lot of steps in this
process but i do want you to try it
there's a lot of like working with your
computer and saving things
so you might get an adult to help you as
well
all right so step number one resizing
the image is done
it has a height of exactly 360 or a
width of exactly 360
and then the other dimension is bigger
the next thing we need to do is we need
to uh
chop it up right so this is my my slides
that showed what
what did with the resize to chop it up
uh there's a tool that i found called
postcron all one word postcron i have no
idea what postcron stands for
image splitter so let's go uh over into
chrome
uh and let's do a search for post cron
uh image splitter hopefully your first
hit
is postcron.com slash image splitter
uh and it takes you to this place and
what you need to do is you need to
upload that image that you just resized
right
so upload image uh looks like i kind of
have to click on it twice so i have to
click on uh
the first one that i have to click on
the second one and you should have this
x360
now what you're going to do this is the
hardest part is you're going to make
this
grid completely fill your image
so here's what i like to do if you grab
it just kind of like in the middle you
can move it around
we want this grid to be exactly 360 tall
or 360 wide just whichever it is it
wants to be a perfect square
if your image is like mine and it's
landscape i'm just going to kind of put
it
right at the top so i'm going to place
like this upper left-hand corner
if you're if your image is portrait
you're going to have to like slam it
over to the side right but i'm going to
slam mine right to the top
and then to take the other corner and as
accurately as you can make it go right
on the very very bottom now this is
tricky
you can go short that's obvious but you
can also go too long so see i went too
long here and i got these like green
things down here
so i want to go exactly on the bottom
and so if you get it perfect you can see
like right now there's little bitty
green nubbins out there
you can see how old i am how i had to
get closer to my computer
if you get it absolutely perfect then
you're going to get
um 120 by 120. if you're off a little
bit
you're gonna get something close which
will work fine but i'm going for perfect
another thing that is annoying is you
might um have trouble with your picture
so you can see how like keegan's face
and bowen's face kind of like barely
made this
feature right so if you if you don't
like how it's laying out pick a
different picture
as soon as you're done click on split
image
and then you click on download image
this time download image really does
download image
so i'm going to call this fisher
birthday
images what it's going to give you is a
zip
file if you've done a lot with computers
you're probably comfortable with zips if
you're new to computers you're probably
new to zips as well
but what a zip file is is it's all your
files
packaged together really tightly
now um sorry there's a lot of steps
this is the easiest method i could find
for you right
so the next thing you need to do is you
need to extract all on the zip
so on a windows computer you'll have to
find it in finder
and there should hopefully be a button
that says extract all
on other computers you'll just have to
double click on it on my mac i just
double click on it
and what it should do is it should chop
your image up into nine
uh tiles so you can see that i did
pretty good
um so each of mine is exactly 120 so i
nailed it
on that on that previous step where like
i was setting the size
it's going to take you a couple of tries
so
i nailed mine i got them all at exactly
120.
the order by the way is sometimes crazy
uh so it looks like
tile one is actually the lower right
corner um and then it goes across the
bottom
for two three and then four
five six and then the top row is going
to be seven hey that's a handsome guy
8 and 9 at the top it's actually
numbered
backwards of what i want we're going to
have to deal with that later
all right so take as long as you need to
try to get that figured out
once you've got your nine images then
you're ready to get started right so
it's like we haven't even started yet dr
fisher you're killing me
so go to scratch.mit.edu
create a new project so longest setup
ever
but it's going to be worth it because
it's cool all right so i am
really hoping that people are successful
with their images i kind of expect
that um the ta office hours like you can
join the zoom meeting
it's going to just light up today with
people that need help with these steps
um that's okay we'll try to make sure
there's extra people
on board for today so uh what i'm gonna
do is i'm gonna actually keep the cat
i know everybody's expecting me to
delete the cat right off but i'm just
gonna
keep the cat i'm gonna go into his
costumes and i'm going to add
my images as different costumes and then
eventually
i'm going to delete the cat costumes but
i'm just going to keep the cat
and just come over here and say choose a
costume
and i'm going to click on upload costume
now what i want to do is i want to go
into that extracted zip file
which has like my one two three four
five six seven eight nine and i want to
bring in all nine as different costumes
of the cat
then what i want to do is i want to
delete the cat because i don't really
need his images
and so now i've got all these images in
here which is cool so you should have
nine total
and i'm going to do some some
organization and clean up the first
thing i want to do is i want them all to
be
vectors so in every single one i'm going
to click on
convert to vector so i'm just going to
do that first
while i'm doing it i'm going to explain
what i'm doing so
with scratch there's two different
drawing modes there's
bitmap mode and then there's vector mode
vector mode is the newer mode
and in general you should use the newer
mode
but it lets you like add something and
then edit it later
bitmap mode does not let you edit it
later so that's why i like vector mode
the next thing i'm going to do is i'm
going to figure out what order my images
are in
so mine came in where number one is the
lower right corner
so it's like 1-1 and then it's
moving across the bottom i know my image
so this is like the bottom middle
and then this is the bottom left and
then it's the the right
on the middle row and then the middle
middle uh and then the left so i know
the order that mine come in
um and strangely it's backwards of what
i wanted right
so the upper left hand corner in my mind
is location one so i've kind of got it
on the board here so i think of this as
like
number one number two number three four
five six seven eight nine
so before we get into the code i'm gonna
do a couple things
first i'm gonna put a number i'm gonna
actually put that number on the image
so the way i do that is i click on text
i decide what color i want to use for my
number
it defaults to purple but you don't have
to use purple you can use any color you
want
i'll make mine red for example
and then i click in here and then i just
type a number one
now the nice thing about vector mode is
that i can like edit this later and it's
not like squished into my picture so i'm
going to get it
to right there which i think is where i
want it
now i numbered this one number one
because i know my
image and i know that this is the upper
left hand corner and so i put a one on
it
now what i'm going to do is i'm going to
number all the other pictures the way i
choose to do it
is i choose to uh copy this i use ctrl
c and then i go to my one that's going
to be two
i paste it on there and then i change
the one to a two but i like to do that
because then it shows up in exactly the
same position every time
so it takes just a little bit of work to
do this so i go through each and every
one
you can pause the video of course as you
need
but they should be in order but they
might be in backwards order
strangely i've tried this on mac i've
tried it on windows i've tried it on
linux i've tried on chromebook
chromebook comes in a different order
than all the others
so that's why we kind of have to do this
manually because yours might have come
in a different a different order right
all right so i'm almost done with mine
uh bottom to top
um after i finish the task i'm going to
have to go back and check it
just to make sure that it that it all
looks right
all right so 9 is my lower right corner
and then oops so there's 9 8
7 6 5
4 3 2 1.
great so that's important the next thing
that i'm going to change is i'm going to
choose to change
the um name of the costume
so right now mine says 9 up here but
this is really
tile 1. being sneaky i'm going to copy
the word tile to my clipboard with ctrl
c
campers will help you do this in a
minute and i'm going to change the names
of all these
to a more logical name right so this i'm
going to call this image
tile 3 i'm going to call this tile 4.
i think you kind of see the pattern the
only one that actually succeeded was
tile 5. it's the only one
that actually had a reasonable name
and so now the names of all my images
uh match and they're appropriate um
and i do that because i'm ocd um
that actually has no value at all
because we we're never gonna refer to
them by their name
we're going to only refer to them by
their index
and the index is also backwards so what
i want to do is i want to drag these
around so you can see that this is
number nine
it needs to go to the very very bottom
you probably have to kind of move it in
two steps so like you kind of move it
about halfway
uh and then you move the rest away but i
can see that tile nine is down on the
bottom
uh tile one uh needs to come to the very
top
uh probably gonna have to do that in two
steps uh nope i got it up to where it's
in the top
so go back and forth and get your tiles
to the correct places
and so hopefully you'll kind of get a
little pattern going and it won't be too
bad
but make sure that it actually is in the
correct order so now my tile one is at
the top
it's called tile one and it's got a one
here tile two
uh all good three four
five 6 7
8 and 9. so
pause the video take as long as you need
to do that
and let's definitely save it because
that was a lot of work so this i'm going
to call my slide puzzle
all right i'm going to help my campers
out hopefully everybody can get this
up and running expect a lot of questions
at the zoom office hours today
that's okay all right so i had to help
my campers out a little bit there that
was no surprise
getting their numbers on and getting
their tiles renamed and things like that
again uh do keep in mind uh that if it's
going badly for you
um you can always uh remix this project
uh to
to just use it right it already had the
numbers in it already had them
rearranged things like that
love for you to be able to do your own
it goes badly use the remix instead of
giving up on the day right
that's kind of what i would say there
all right so uh now we're ready to go
um so you can leave whichever costume
selected you want it honestly doesn't
matter it's going to show up over
here but that honestly doesn't matter uh
and we're ready to uh to hop
into the code uh we're going to be doing
code
on uh this one sprite that we have which
is currently called sprite1
i don't like that name i'm going to
rename him to tile
so i just like that name better so now
he's named tile
and what we're going to do is we're
going to do some code on this sprite
and then some code on the backdrop and
just like our previous games we're going
to make use of clones really
heavily because we're just going to have
this one tile that has different images
it's going to be really creative
by the way the backdrop if you want you
can choose to leave it white
or you can actually add an image back
here the backdrop doesn't really affect
anything i always kind of like this
heart one right so i'm going to put a
heart back there
just because it like shows love right
backdrop completely optional i choose to
stick one on
uh let's go ahead and start into the
code
that's happening on the the backdrop
sometimes i call it a backdrop sometimes
i call it a stage
so our first goal here is going to be
very similar to what we did with the
lawnmower
so we're going to try to plant all these
things
so that forms a grid so if you remember
the lawn mower
the first thing we did with the
lawnmowers we did a bunch of math right
this one the math is easier so each of
these tiles
is exactly 120 across so this way is 120
uh and then this way is 120 as well
um and it turns out that you're going to
need to know where the centers are of
each tile
um and so if this is 120 and then this
is 120 then the distance from here to
there
is 60. uh and then the distance from
here to there is 60. by the way it looks
like there's a little gap in here but
there's not they're actually smushed
together
uh so camper is the easiest question of
the day what's 60 plus 60
110 120 uh and then this one's just
right at zero
uh and then this one is down so it's
actually negative 60
um plus a negative 60. so what's this
one down here
negative 100 negative 120 and then the
math this direction kind of works the
same so you've got a negative 120
a zero and a positive 120. so the math
is actually much easier this time
because the centers of these things it's
either at like negative 120 positive 120
or 0 positive 120
but it's always like 0 or 120 or a
negative 120. so the math is easier
so let's go ahead and see if we can do
some of the tricks that we did with
lawnmower
on the backdrop so the first thing we
need is we need a couple variables if
you remember how the
how the graphs worked we need a variable
i'm going to call this one the
placement x
interestingly whenever you're on the
backdrop it doesn't even give you that
choice of like
should it be just for this sprite or
should it be for all sprites if you're
on the backdrop it's always for
everybody
so i'm going to make a variable called
placement x
i'll make another variable called
placement y
and if you remember the trick that we
used with lawnmower is we kind of like
set these variables
uh to like where it was going to get
placed then we made a clone
and then we moved the clone to that
variable you remember that
you remember that campers all right
um so we need a placement x and
placement y and this time we need one
more
we need to know what costume number
we need costume i misspelt
again you can see that my preferred
naming convention for variables that i'm
gonna hide is this camel case
um and so our goal is um on the backdrop
um let's start by placing just this top
one in the corner
and then we'll place the whole row and
then we'll place the whole grid right
so what i want to do is i want to go to
events when green flag clicked
so no shock we're going to start with
the win green flag click that's how we
start like every program
and we're going to set these variables
so i'm going to drag over three set
commands
and the first one i'm going to set the
placement x and then the placement y
and then the costume number so for this
very first one see if you can figure out
how you would set these three things so
how are you going to set placement x how
are you going to set placement y and how
you're going to set the cost remember
take a minute and see if you can do it
on your own
all right so my campers actually did
pretty good with it uh so the
x is negative 120 the y is positive 120
and this is going to be costume number
one
um and then what i like to do is i like
to just because we had this problem with
the lawnmower
is oh i like to make the clone i need to
make that first right so create clone of
tile
and then i like to have a short delay
i don't know if this short delay is
actually necessary this time
it was for the lawnmower and so i'm just
going to stick it on right so i'm just
going to put a short delay after i place
a tile
if i run this code right now nothing's
going to happen because my tile
doesn't actually use these variables so
let's go into our tile code
and let's actually write a little bit
over here
so our tile code is going to be when i
start as clone
so i've kind of seen this pattern a few
times
that you when you're clone you don't
care about the green flag you care about
when i start his clone
and what he's going to do is he's going
to use those variables so he's got this
go to xy
um and then he's also got this switch
costume
2 command so these are the things he's
going to do oh and then he's going to
also
show up after that right so remember
that with clones
and i can do this now here's the
original i'm actually going to hide the
original
which is very common to do with clones
i'm going to go to where i need to go
i'm going to set my costume and then i'm
going to show these values are not
correct though i need to use these
variables
so i need to use the placement x i need
to use the placement y
and then the fun thing about costumes is
you can refer to them by name
so you can see i've got got names for
all mine here or you can refer to it by
number and that's the the number that
you see in this upper left hand corner
here
so it's interesting that the names
actually didn't matter at all so if you
went through and you changed them all
then great but if not
we're not using the names at all so if i
run this
my tile should now show up in the corner
which is cool
these variables are all in the way so
i'm going to hit the green check boxes
on these
to hide these variables also this is
optional
there's the built-in variable called my
variable if you want to you can right
click on this and you can delete
the my variable variable we're going to
have
enough variables that we don't need the
extra clutter today
all right now from here uh you can kind
of see that what you could do
is you could right click on this and
duplicate it
and you could um you know just change it
to the next one over so the placement x
on this next one over
is going to be a zero and then the
costume is gonna be two
right so if you uh ran this
uh it should be pretty easy to put one
and two together
it kind of looks like minor disjoint but
but it actually worked and you could
repeat that nine times um and it and it
would work to place all the grids
campers do you think that's what we're
gonna do no no
what are we gonna do what are you gonna
what are we gonna do instead we're
computer scientists what do you guys
think we're gonna do
um if else repeats yeah
loops and and fun things like that um
and not only are we gonna use
loops and things like that but we're
gonna use functions as well because i
like functions
so let's start off by going to my blocks
and click on make a block i just like to
practice with functions
and so this function is going to be to
add a row
so add row is the name of our function
uh you can see that whenever you make a
function it kind of like gives you a
spot to
to put stuff into the insides of the
functions and the ability to call it
here
now i'm going to do a little bit of
refactoring first i'm going to take off
this bottom part that was just kind of
like the second tile that was just kind
of showed that you could do it
and then i'm going to kind of like pull
this one apart a little bit
so some things are going to go into add
row and some things are going to stay
here
so placement x that goes into add row
because that's going to be like the x
things that's for a single row
uh placement y that goes into when the
green flag is clicked
costume number setting it to 1 that goes
into the green flag clicked
and then this stuff is going to go
inside of a loop over here
so i kind of took my code and i broke it
down some
i happen to know that the x stuff
happens like inside of a row so it's
inside of the row area
whereas all these other things are
outside of it so here's what we're going
to do we're going to call
add row and we're going to make it work
how many tiles are there any true
campers three
three so we're going to make a loop that
repeats how many times
three times you got it so inside of that
loop
uh we're going to create a clone of the
tile
and you'll notice that for the first
tile the placement x and the placement y
are correct
if we just did this loop right now so if
i ran it right now it's going to be a
disaster because it's just going to put
number one number one and number one all
in the same spot right
so what i'm going to need to do is after
i place number one
i'm gonna have to change some of the
variables so let's go into variables
and we're gonna have to change the
costume number
placement x
so we're going to change the costume
number by one because it's going to go
one two three four five you get the idea
and we're going to change the placement
x all right campers how much we're going
to change the placement x by
so from here to get over to the next one
120 120 i was waiting to see if you're
going to get it right or if you were
going to say 60.
yeah so we're going to place this one
we're going to move over 120 and we're
going to place this one
going to move over 120 and place this
one so that's going to be the whole row
so if i go ahead and run this i can see
that that whole row just like popped up
all right so mine came up great uh
keegan's actually came up
crazy um it's interesting you know i
said that names of the um
the names of the tiles didn't matter it
turns out that if they're numbers
that are numbered different that does
matter so make sure that if you do have
a name for each uh each costume
make sure it's either the matching
number uh or it's something different
like tile so
thank you for that keegan all right so
now uh we got one row done
uh now we're going to do many rows now
we could
uh as you know kind of like manually do
them
is that what we're gonna do no way how
many rows are there
three so we're gonna need a repeat three
so go and drag over a repeat three
command
so repeat three oops i'm
inside the repeat three uh we're going
to add row
which is going to be great if we were to
run this right now would add
one two three and then it would right on
top of it put in a four five six and
then right on top of that put a seven
eight nine
so obviously after we add a row we're
going to change the placement y so it
comes down
so let's go into variables change
the placement y
what's the value for placement y gonna
need to get changed by
120. oh not 120 that would go up
negative 120 there we go so negative
120.
uh and so now if this works uh it's
going to make your your whole grid
which i think is pretty cool right so
it's actually like taking your picture
and recombined it
now it's funny that in this game
it's like we started with a complete
picture then we chopped it up
and we made it all separate tiles and
then the first thing we did in the code
is we put it back together
um and then the next thing we're going
to do is now we're going to scramble it
all up
so um we don't actually want it to be an
order we actually want it to be
scrambled up
we also don't need tile number nine
and so we're gonna go in and make some
of those things happen so the first
thing i'm gonna do is i'm gonna make
tile number nine
not show up so to do that i'm gonna go
into and make an if statement
i'm actually going to use this one right
here so this if condition
then and i'm going to have two cases and
my condition is going to be
is the costume number number nine so i'm
going to find in operators i'm going to
find the equality one
and i'm curious if the costume number
is number nine so
normally i place it and then i wait for
a little bit
but costume number nine is gonna be
different so i'm gonna
i'm gonna re-um redo my loop here a
little bit
i'm gonna say uh these two always happen
so they're kind of like below my fl
statement so they are always going to
happen
but this creating a clone is going to
only happen if it's not costume number
nine
if i put it in the top that'd be when it
is costume 9 so i want to create a clone
down here when it's not costume 9. and
then now that i've got
this whole thing set up i'm going to put
it back and tied the repeat loop
refactoring code is always just a little
bit confusing because you have something
that looks like this
and if you were able to track what i was
doing exactly you were able to do at the
same time as me
but more important is that you can look
at it now and you can see that it's
correct so i've got a repeat three
i've got an if i don't have anything up
here right now and then i only create
the clone there but i always change it
if you run it again it should
successfully just leave off
tile number nine which is good now tile
number nine
is actually important to us um it's our
blank
right so we need to keep track of where
our blank is at at all times
because whenever somebody clicks on a
tile they're going to swap with the
blank
so we're going to make a couple
variables we're going to make a variable
called blank
x and then another variable called
blank y
i don't need them to show up on the
screen so i'm going to click on this
little blue checkbox and hide them
strangely i found that if you show them
there can be a bug so definitely make
sure you hide those
and what i'm going to do is in this gap
right here i'm going to set
blank x and blank y so blank
x and then blank y
and they're going to get set to whatever
the placement x
and placement y are so wherever this
tile
should have gone in at we're gonna save
that off as blank x and blank y
and then we can use that knowledge uh
later in our code which is gonna be cool
all right now comes some fun stuff so
now like you're on day four of this camp
uh the gloves kind of come off against
coding we're going to do we're going to
start doing some crazier things
so what i want to do is i want to
shuffle these tiles all around
so here's my my plan i'm going to
randomly select
a number and then i'm going to move it
into the blank if it's a valid thing to
move
and i'm going to do that to shuffle it
up how many times do you guys think we
ought to do that just to kind of shuffle
it up
any guesses a million times so the first
guess was a million times
so you can go into control uh and you
can bring over repeat loop
the first guess was a million times uh
that would actually
take uh very long right um so here's
what we're gonna do
bob and i have played with this and we
think that 300
is the perfect number for testing though
i'm going to only use 100 so i'm going
to do 100 shuffles
and that way it's faster when i'm
testing but before i ship my game i'm
going to change this to 300 sound good
so this will make testing faster and
then the thing that i'm going to do a
hundred times
is i'm going to randomly pick
a costume number so i'm going to say set
costume number and i'm going to set it
to a random number
so i'm going to go into operators pick
random
and the random number that i pick
could be one through eight so there's no
reason to do number nine because there
is no number nine so i'm gonna randomly
pick
one through eight and then i'm gonna
broadcast an event
so i'm gonna go into events uh and i'm
gonna say broadcast
and the message i'm gonna broadcast i'm
gonna make a new message
called shuffle so at this point in the
code
there's eight clones out there they're
all gonna listen for shuffle
right and i'm gonna broadcast it a
hundred times in a row real fast i'm
gonna say
shuffle shuffle shuffle you get the idea
and then
each tile is going to have a job they're
going to say
um was it me that was total shuffle um
and then they're going to check to see
if they're with if they're touching the
blank or not
and if they are they're going to swap
does that sound sound good
so let's go uh from here so we're
broadcasting shuffle 100 times
we're picking a random tile to actually
listen to it
so let's go into our tile code
so in our tile code what we're going to
do is we're going to say when i receive
shuffle so there's
eight clones of this right and they all
have different costume numbers
the first thing we want to know is is
this message for me so we're going to
have an if statement
and we're going to decide is this
message for me
um and we're going to check that with
the equals operator
so he called out a number so he called
out a costume number
and the question is is that costume
number
my costume number so if it was my
costume number then i need to do
something
how do i know if it's my costume number
well over in looks
each clone has this variable called
costume number
that's perfect so if the number he
called
so if the number he called his costume
number um if it was me
then i need to do something the thing
i'm going to do i'm going to put in a
function because i like functions
so let's go ahead and make a function
and we'll call this function
try to move so
if we're next to the blank we will move
if we're not next to the blank then we
won't move so i'm going to make a
function called try to move
so i'm going to call it right here so if
it's my number that he called then try
to move
all right now it's right try to move so
the first thing try to move has to
figure out is they have to figure out if
they're next to
the blank so let's look at my board here
so my board doesn't have a tile nine
anymore
um it's instead got this blank and this
blank has a value that's right here
so based on the board that i'm looking
at here campers which tiles can move
so which ones can move into this blank
six six and eight that's right so
they're the only ones that can do it
so the question is how how are they
special um
and they're special in my opinion
because their
centers are close to this center
and the distance that they are away from
the center is they're 120 away from the
center
and so what we're going to say is we're
going to we're going to look at
rx compared to his x we're going to look
at our y compared to his y
and if the grand total is less than uh
maybe like 121 or 130
then we know that we can move mckinley
do you have a question
what if they're all hers what if they're
all hers i keep saying him so
yeah i should work on my my pronouns
thank you for keeping me honest there
now there's also ones that are like way
up here um and this one is
is too far right so um here's our plan
we're going to figure out how far we are
away so we're going to do a comparison
between the blanks
x and y versus
my current x position and y position
so these are the the variables that are
going to be involved in this
um and what we want to do is we want to
know the the delta between the x's and
the delta between the y's
so to get a delta that's uh subtraction
so i'm going to grab a subtraction
symbol here
and a subtraction symbol here so i'm
going to say blank x
minus x position blank y
minus y position so this is going to
give me the
the delta x or the delta y
now it might be a positive number might
be a negative number and i don't i don't
care if it's positive or negative i
always want a positive
do you guys know what function will will
make something always be a positive
all right i think keegan's got it
absolute value that's right i took a
little coaxing here but it's called an
absolute value
so scratch has this thing it's like can
do all kinds of crazy math things but
the one we want is abs
because it stands for absolute value you
may have never seen absolute value in
school yet
but believe me you will right so i want
the absolute value of the delta x
and the absolute value of the delta y
now what i'm going to choose to do is
i'm going to choose to add these two
together
so to add them i need the plus operator
make sure that you get the plus operator
when i prep this i grab the
multiplication operator trust me that
did not work right
so i need the plus operator and i'm just
going to add
these two together by the way whenever
your your operators kind of get complex
make sure you always grab it from the
middle
so this one the middle is the of so i'm
going to drop this into one half
and then i'm going to grab the of here
and drop this into the other half
and now for this big one if i want to
move it i have to make sure i grab the
plus right so
so we're not done yet what we want to do
is we want to see if this whole thing
is less than i'm going to use a
threshold of 130 right
and the 130 will make sure to pick off
everybody including the diagonal
but that'll give you a little
flexibility in case your images are a
little too big right
so i'm going to say if
this whole thing is less than 130 so i'm
going to go ahead and grab a less than
and 130. so if this whole thing so i've
got to grab it from the plus here
and drop it into there it's so big it
doesn't even fit on the screen anymore
right
so if that whole thing is less than 130
then
i must be next to the blank and this
algorithm will work even if the blanks
in the middle then it'll figure out that
these four can move right so it's kind
of a smart algorithm
so now what happens if if we are a match
if we're a match we've got a swap with
the blank um swapping
is a very popular thing that happens in
computer science
so uh let's see here so let's say i had
two variables i had a
is five and b is seven
if i wanted to swap them i could say
that a is equal to b
and b is equal to a
campers would this work in code
so this is an interesting problem that
happens in code let's let's step through
what happens just because i like it
so this is the values of a and b like as
this code executes
so right here a is five after this line
a
is still five of course but now b is
seven
after this line of code runs it says b
is equal to a so it actually
reassigns a so a is now seven
but b is still seven and then this line
does nothing
so um this direct
change a is b and b is a doesn't work
which is interesting because of how
sequential programming works
and the trick to fix this problem is you
need a temporary variable
so i'm going to call it t so i'm going
to save off the value of a
into this variable t that's a temporary
variable
now i can blow away a and then at the
bottom here i just have to use t
and this trick does work if i were to
put t over here
we'd have like five seven and five
and then we blow away a and then we set
b to that temporary variable
and then interestingly at the end of the
day we don't care about that temporary
variable
so it's a very common thing in computer
science
where you want to swap two things and
you
you can't just swap them like you would
think you have to make a temporary
variable
all right let's just do it right so we
want to swap
my position with the blanks position so
that's our goal
and we're going to have to make a
temporary variable which we just learned
about
so let's go and make two variables we'll
call one temp x
and then the other one is going to be
temp y
so we need a temporary variable for the
x and temporary variable y
i don't want to show them so i'm going
to hide them
and now i'm going to do a bunch of steps
so the first thing i'm going to do is
i'm going to set my temporary variables
so i'm going to say temp x and temp y
and the thing that i'm going to choose
to save off is i'm going to choose to
save off the x position and y position
so i'm going to save off x position
and y position
so the nice thing is is that once i save
them off into a temporary variable
then i can blow them away right so i can
change them
the fastest way to change them is this
command that says
go to xy
interestingly you could also set them
individually with this like set x and
set y but we'll just kind of do it
all in one shot and the thing we're
going to set them to is we're going to
move this tile
to wherever the blank is at does that
make sense
so this tile is going to move and it's
going to move to wherever the blank was
at
and then the blank is going to be where
this tile was so they they swapped it's
called a swap right
so now i need to set
blank x and blank y
to those temporary variables temp x
and temp y i can't set them to x and y
anymore because those those have been
changed by this blue line right
but i can use those temporary variables
so it's kind of a fun crazy thing so
i'm going to pause it and ask my campers
if they understand this code
because it's kind of complex right so
make sure you can look at this
and explain what's going on
all right well i should see if this
works uh so when i click this green flag
what should happens it should shuffle
them a hundred times
and so it happens kind of quick uh and
it shuffles them around
you'll notice that they're not shuffled
great they're shuffled uh good enough
for testing
eventually we're going to change this
number to be 300
uh which i think will shuffle them a
little bit better so like you can see
before my number one was still in the
upper left
but with 300 it shuffles them a little
better i think that one shuffled enough
uh but but i'm going to actually leave
it at 100 for my testing
that way it's faster and then as soon as
i finish my game i'll put it back to
300.
does that sound good by the way it's
also good to take breaks every so often
so as soon as you see that this works
um maybe take a break right so just take
a take a break pause the video walk away
and come back a little bit later
all right are you back from your break
uh let's do some more stuff so the next
thing that i think really
needs to happen is i want to be able to
click on a tile
and have it glide into position right so
i want it to kind of glide over
so let's see if we can implement that
and to be honest that's actually one of
the last required things for today
my campers are going to have to do the
whole thing but after this step you
you could be done after today because it
is pretty big so let's make it to where
when you click on one of these
it'll glide into position really nicely
so here's what i want to do i want to go
into my tile code
and you can see that my tile code
already has like a when i receive
shuffle when i start as clone so it's
kind of got all these things
and we're going to make something else
we're going to get an event
called when the sprite is clicked so
when the sprite is clicked what do we
want to do
so what we're going to do is actually
similar in many ways to shuffle
because we're going to try to move
that's going to be our main thing
we don't have to check where the ones
click we know where the ones clicked
and so like when this tile is clicked we
want to try to move
let's go ahead and try it with just that
additional code so it does my shuffling
and so now oh i had this goof this
sometimes happens i've got a goof to
where i've got two
holes i'm going to pretend like i didn't
see that and just run it again so you
can do the same but that happens to you
so right now what should happen if i
click on seven it should try to move
one should try to move and it should
work but if i click on like four it
shouldn't do anything
right only the ones that are next to the
tile
uh can move so i think that that
actually uh
is doing pretty well it looks like i can
play the game if i wanted right now
i could use my algorithm to try to solve
it i'm not going to right now but i
could right so i could actually like try
to solve this thing
instead what i want to do is i want when
i click it i want it to smoothly glide
right so you can see that right now it's
just going there it's just snapping over
i think it would be cool to have kind of
like a slide animation
so how do we do that so uh the first
thing we need to do is this go block in
here
needs to have an if statement around it
so here's what i'm going to do i'm going
to go into control
and i'm going to grab an if else
so sometimes i want to get there like
immediately and then other times i want
to glide
so i'm going to go ahead and break this
up a little bit
and i want just this blue line in here
and then i want to put that on the top
sorry that on the bottom that on the top
so this refactoring thing again and this
is going to be in this area
i'm going to kind of put it all back in
so i'm still going to do the swap so
same thing as before
it's just instead of a go to i'm going
to use a different command
called glide 2
x y so sometimes i'm going to go there
and sometimes i'm going to glide there
now
operator or variables here i'm going to
move in
blank x and blank y
and this glide i'm going to glide in 0.2
seconds
so sometimes i want to go sometimes i
want to glide
how am i going to decide whether it
should be a go or a glide
so what i want to do is i want to pass
into this function
an argument this is something new so
right click
so your right mouse button right click
on this word define
and click on edit and what i want to do
is i don't just want to have a function
i want to
add an input i'm going to add this
number or text so i'm click right here
and i'm going to give this argument a
name i'm going to call it
go or glide and you can make it say like
uh go over glide like this but what
we're gonna do is go is gonna be a one
so i'm gonna say like go one or glide
two so i'm gonna call it go one
or glide two so they're gonna pass in a
one or a two one for go
two for glide and so now you can see
that it says up here uh try to move go
or glide right there
and then when i call it you can see that
it added this thing so this
when i'm shuffling it's a go so go is
one
and then when i click it it's a glide so
glide is two
so go one glide two
now i need to use that variable
in here so i'm gonna go to operators and
grab an equals
so where's my equals operator so if and
then this is tricky you actually grab it
from here
and put it down there which i think
that's kind of tricky how you just kind
of do it from right right inside here
so if go or glide is a one
then we want to go there that way
shuffling is fast right
um but if it's a click we want to glide
there so let's try it so right now i
shuffle
and it's fast um it did the two blank
thing i'm gonna pretend like i didn't
see that
moving on so now uh whenever i click it
uh things should
glide to the correct position which is
cool
uh and now what we're gonna do is we're
gonna give you the option
of adding the extra features or not so
you can see that right now the game is
completely playable
uh and you you can win it uh which is
cool
if you would like to be done right here
today
you could be pat yourself in the back go
do something
else call it done if you wanted to
though we've got some extra features for
you
so for example it feels unsatisfying uh
that you
win and nothing happens right and so
it'd be nice to add that feature
it also would be neat to add kind of
like a moves counter so you know how
long it took you to do it
um and so those added features is what
we're going to add next
and it is just a little bit complicated
so if you feel like calling it today
great job we'll see you tomorrow for the
final day of coding camp
if you've got the energy to do these
last things then
let's go ahead and do them together so
what i want to do first is i want to
check to see if we solve the
puzzle or not so how do we check to see
if we solve the puzzle
well each tile needs to know if it's in
the correct position or not
and to do this we're going to use
something called an array an array is
new
so if you go into variables in the past
we've used all kinds of variables
we've made a fair number of blocks as
well but see where it says
make a list so here's what we're going
to do
each of these tiles has a certain x
position it's supposed to be in
so this is supposed to be at negative
120 0 and then positive 120
they also have a specific y they're
supposed to be in this top row the y is
always 120
and so we're going to make um a
list of what the correct x's and correct
y's are
so go ahead and do this with me go and
go into your backdrop because that's
where we're going to be putting the code
click on make a list so
this list is going to be the correct
x i could say correct x values but it's
going to be correct x
so this is going to be a list of correct
x values and it's going to have the
values like negative 120
0 positive 120 negative 120 0 positive
120 negative 120 0 positive 120 so let's
have nine values total so
those are the correct x list values
and you can see it shows up on the
screen we're going to eventually hide it
but let's go ahead and
leave it for now and then we're going to
make another one this is probably no
surprise
called correct y i mean it's going to
have a list with 9 items and it's going
to be 120 120 120
0 0 0 negative 120 negative 120 negative
120.
so those are going to be the values so
we have to make this list
the easiest way to make this list is to
cleverly put
into your code where you should clear
the array
and where you should put things in so
we're going to clear the arrays
at the very start so to clear the arrays
we're just going to say delete all of
correct
x delete all of correct y
and so that's going to make sure that
they start empty so right now they're
empty but we're going to guarantee they
start empty
and then we're going to add things at
very appropriate
points so let's do this um i'm going to
drag over add thing to correct x
and i'm going to put it inside my add
row function
inside the repeat 3 loop just before the
if statement so you can see where it's
out there
and so what i'm going to do is i'm going
to add
placement x to the correct
x list and i'm going to add placement y
to the correct y list and so my goal
here is
that these two lists that you see which
are currently empty
they're going to get filled in uh with
the what are the solution locations
so when i run it it'll still do like the
other things in the background
but the thing i care about is that this
filled in with a negative 120 0
120 negative 120 0 120 uh you can see
the pattern
and then this one's like the 120s the
zeros and the negative 120s
so we've now we know where things should
be
now i'm going to hide them
now what i want to do is once i do a
glide so i'm going to go over to my tile
whenever i do a glide i'm going to
have people count themselves so i'm
going to say hey how many tiles are
correct
so i'm going to broadcast out that
everybody should count themselves
and i'm going to make a variable that
keeps track of how many are correct
so let's do it then it'll make more
sense first click on make a variable
this variable is going to be num correct
again there's lots of different ways to
do variables i choose to use camel case
mush them together
instead of spelling out the word number
i just type num correct
so i've got that variable and whenever i
glide
i'm going to set it to zero
so after a glide i'm going to set
num correct to zero and then i'm gonna
broadcast that everybody needs to count
themselves
so i'm gonna broadcast a message uh that
says like
um check for
win so everybody's going to count
themselves we're going to see how many
of us are correct
and if there's eight correct then that
means that we've won the game
so um let's go ahead and keep going but
i'm going to check in on my campers
first
before i before i do this next step so i
checked in on my campers and keegan was
no longer on his computer keegan are you
calling it done for today
yup so he was happy with the previous
thought what about you sis
i'm adding the extra piece yeah she's
going strong enough the extra features
and that did not surprise me
at all knowing my kiddos but i did want
to point out that it is okay that if you
if you chose to stop
so i've got um numcrack set to zero and
then i broadcast
check for win so the idea is i'm just
screaming hey everybody
see if you're in the right spot um and
then we're gonna see how many of us
are in the right spot so uh down here
we're gonna have to say
when i receive so when i receive
check for a win so all tiles do this
they have to see if they're in the right
spot and so what we need to do
is we need to compare our current
x and y so we're going to compare our
current x and y
to the correct x and y so i'm going to
go into
variables i just like to
get the things that i need right so i
need
item 1 of correct x
and item one of correct y
now this is a list right there's nine
different items in there
i don't always want number one i want
the appropriate one for my costume
number
so like if i'm costume 4 i want to
compare against the fourth item in the
array
so i don't want a one here i want to
actually go into looks
and i want my costume number
so costume number costume number so if
my
x is equal to the correct
x for my costume number and my y
is equal to the correct y for my costume
number
then and only then i can add one to the
number correct
so i'm going to need some operators here
so i'm going to have to check these for
equality
so i'm going to go ahead and grab an
equality here inequality here so i'm
going to say if my x
is equal to this and my y
is equal to that so if that is true and
that is true so i need an and statement
now
again these these things get really
complex right so you got to grab it from
like the
the middle of it so big i can barely
even see it
and so and i've got to zoom out so i'm
just to see my whole thing so if my x
is equal to the correct x and my y is
equal to the correct y
then i can do something so i need an if
statement
so i got to grab it from the and
then what i'm going to do is i'm going
to report that i was correct and the way
that i report that i was correct as i go
to variables
and i change the number correct
so num correct by one so you can see
that
somebody did a glide he reset it to zero
and then he told everybody to count
themselves so let's go ahead and see if
this
is working so if i run it now it does
some shuffling
if i get my two blank thing i just click
it again um and so as soon as i do a
glide so i'm gonna glide the five
tile over um everybody should count
themselves
and so if we look at mine we can see
that uh 1 2 and 3 are all wrong
4 5 is correct right here and then 6 7
and 8 are all wrong
let's go ahead and do another one i'm
going to put 4 is in the correct
position
and now 7 is in the correct position and
now as soon as i slide eight over it
should go up to three so
test it however you want um but the
number correct
should be getting tracked now um if you
wanted to solve the whole puzzle you
could
but that of course takes a little bit of
time i'm gonna go ahead and solve mine
just for fun
i've done these uh algorithms enough
that i can usually get them done in a
timely fashion right
so i'm gonna go ahead and click here
um and so right there it should be eight
so there
num correct is equal to eight nothing
happened
when num correct was equal to eight
because i haven't written that code yet
right
so it's all about writing the code to
make these things happen
mckimley are you caught up or do you
fall behind so she's good so we're still
going strong
so who's going to check to see if we're
correct um
it could actually be about anybody i'm
going to choose
for the backdrop to check if i'm correct
and just because i can i'm going to
actually just make another
win green flag clicked over here
when this green flag is clicked i'm
going to make sure that my
num correct variable is set to zero so
i'm going to say
set num correct equal to zero
this is because like when the last game
finishes if it was eight when the last
one finishes i want to make sure to
clear that off
and i want to forever check
if the number correct
is equal to eight so i want to check
if it's equal to eight i did that really
fast uh but it's because i think that
you're kind of getting to the point
where you can do some of these things
right
so i'm not just checking once it's not a
single if statement i'm just forever
checking
to see if the number correct is equal to
eight if it is
then i've won the game right um and when
i win the game i want to do a couple of
things
uh one is i need to play a sound that's
probably the most important
i think the sound i'm going to play is
cheer
so i have to add cheer to my library
so it's kind of loud but uh but cheer
worked
so i i added that to my sounds like
we've done before and then i'm gonna
play it over here
uh so i'm gonna play it until it's done
so i'm going to play cheer
i'm also going to bring in the ninth
tile
so if you remember when we started this
lecture
like an hour ago the way we bring in a
tile
is we set um we set three things we set
the placement x placement x
the placement y and the costume number
and then we um create a clone
which is in control
again i i brought those in kind of fast
it's because only
only like the true troopers have made it
this far right
and what i want to set the placement x
and placement y to
and the costume number is well the
costume number is going to be 9
because that that's going to be where
it's at and then i want this spot right
here
this spot right here is actually saved
off in the variables
blank x
and blank y by the way i don't really
need to show that number correct so i'm
going to hit this green check box to get
rid of it
so when i win i want to
load in the ninth tile so i set
placement x and placement y i set the
costume number
i say create clone and that'll actually
bring him in
and then i want to play a sound and then
i'm gonna wait for a minute or wait for
a few seconds maybe like two or three
seconds
um and then i'm gonna stop all
and i'm just waiting for two or three
seconds just so you can enjoy the
victory while you're there
bob likes for this number to be like a
full minute so he does like 60 seconds
whatever you want i'm just going to do
three seconds because that'll be plenty
and i think i'm ready to give it a go
now i will say that in order to test
this i do have to like get them
all right to test it so if it fails i'm
going to like
really regret how hard it was to test if
you
want to test it easier change this
number eight to like two or something
like that
i think that i can do uh do the whole
thing uh so i'm gonna go ahead and
just try it alright so i'm almost there
so as soon as i slide this up uh i
should be able to see my
my victory sequence so i slide it up
it'll work great and then after my three
seconds uh it goes away
so i'm going to help my camper out oh
man i just learned something great from
mckinley
so a great way to test this is to
shuffle it less
so where it says like repeat 100 or
something over here just shuffle it like
three or four times and then play your
game
and now it's actually like super easy to
win
[ __ ] brilliant nicely done
so um i think that mine is going pretty
good
i'm going to crank this up to 300 now if
it didn't work
you're just going to have to look at the
code that we did recently rewind the
video
[ __ ] had a goof here on on correct y
that we fixed
but i think that we're ready for the
last thing
which is to track how many moves we've
got so i'm going to go into variables
i'm going to make my final variable
called moves i'm going to set
moves to be zero somewhere again i don't
really care where you set it to zero
i'll tell you what i've just been
goofing around over here so i'll go
ahead and do this i'm going to say
set moves to zero
moves actually i'm going to uh click on
it here or sorry right click on it and
say
large readout just so it's actually it's
funny that large readout is smaller i
find that funny
but every time i move so every time i
glide a tile
uh i'm going to increment moves by one
so i'm going to change
so every time i do a glide i'm going to
change moves
by one now if it
works mckinley got a messed up somewhere
question
all right so i um i went a little too
fast uh so i'm going to go back and help
mckinley i'll tell you what i'll just
i'll just say what i said
so i created a variable called moves
i set moves to be 0 somewhere in the
code i chose to set it to be zero
on the stage right after a green flag
check so that just sets it to zero
and then i increment it when i do a
glide
and so the glide happens inside the tile
right after a glide then i change moves
by one
and so now as i move it should just keep
track of how many moves that i've got
that fix you up [ __ ] so now
it's going to like keep track of how
long i take to do this algorithm
uh which you know can sometimes be quick
and it sometimes can be disastrous
um so i'm gonna go ahead and see if i
can finish mine and see what it is
you could also choose to add like a
fastest time or something like that
but hey you know what that's up to you
i i would recommend that you click on
share
and so uh if you share it then other
people can visit it
looks like it took just a minute to
share there and then this url you can
send to friends and family
and you can see how things work i
suppose i ought to see
uh one last time how long it takes to do
my algorithm here
all right so i think i've got mine
towards almost solved uh and so i put it
together
um and mine works um what about my
campers
uh so campers let's see how you did so
keegan obviously
um isn't gonna have the win thing in his
uh because he chose the uh to finish
when i said it's fine oh look at that
picture
tim and his dog duvy excellent very nice
i love the
i love the picture so uh if you ever
want to do the win thing i can always do
it with you later okay
very nice king did you enjoy today's
yeah do you like the slide puzzle
was it a little more complicated than
anything we've ever done before
all right mckinley let's see yours oh
she's got uh all these these cool horses
very nice very nice that's cool
did you learn some new things today sis
yeah yeah today was crazy
all right so i want to say a couple
things uh and then we'll turn you loose
uh so the final things that i want to
say today
are that you've done a lot of crazy
things with clones now
you learn how to use arrays and with
code you can do a lot more than you
think right so like
a complex puzzle like this is totally
something that scratch can handle
and it's really kind of cool all right
go share your link with
friends and family let them try their
puzzle don't tell them the algorithm
right just make them try to figure it
out and then you can use the algorithm
and show off
show off your skills all right loved
having you can't wait to see you
tomorrow for the final day of our coding
camp
see you then bye